<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the true Christian religion in opposition to the abominations of popery in a sermon upon Ezek. 21: 24,25,26,27 : being the text appointed by the Pope for Master Whitebread, one of the popish conspirators, to preach upon the accomplishing of their wicked design for taking away the life of His Most Sacred Majesty ... / by J. Thomas, Rect. of S. Nicholas.</title>
            <author>Thomas, J. (John)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11254633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11254633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47158</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47158)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1451:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the true Christian religion in opposition to the abominations of popery in a sermon upon Ezek. 21: 24,25,26,27 : being the text appointed by the Pope for Master Whitebread, one of the popish conspirators, to preach upon the accomplishing of their wicked design for taking away the life of His Most Sacred Majesty ... / by J. Thomas, Rect. of S. Nicholas.</title>
                  <author>Thomas, J. (John)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Isaac Cleave ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel XXI, 24-27 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE True Chriſtian RELIGION, In Oppoſition to the Abominations of <hi>POPERY;</hi> IN A SERMON Upon <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21. 24, 25, 26, 27. Being the Text appointed by the <hi>Pope</hi> for Maſter <hi>Whitebread,</hi> one of the Popiſh Conſpirators, to preach upon the accompliſhing of their Wicked Deſign, for taking away the Life of his Moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty: Wherein the King, the Church, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his Majeſties Laws, Conſtitutions, and true Proteſtant Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> are clearly Juſtified; and the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Church, and Popiſh Faction of <hi>Rome,</hi> are juſtly charged to be guilty of the like Dreadful Curſe in the New, as hath been denounc'd againſt Revolted <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Old Teſtament. By <hi>J. Thomas</hi> Rect. of S. <hi>Nicholas;</hi> Preached at <hi>Cardiffe,</hi> Before the Bayliffs and Aldermen there. <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1678/9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iſaac Cleave,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> next to <hi>Serjeants-Inn</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. JANE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47158:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EZEK. XXI. 24, 25, 26, 27.</bibl>
                  <p>24. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, becauſe you have made your iniquity to be remembred, in that your tranſgreſſions be diſcovered, ſo that in all your doings your ſins do appear; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay that ye are come to remembrance, ye ſhall be taken with the hand.</p>
                  <p>25. And thou prophane wicked Prince of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> whoſe day is come when iniquity ſhall have an end.</p>
                  <p>26. Thus ſaith the Lord God, remove the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, and take away the Crown; this ſhall not be the ſame; exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high.</p>
                  <p>27. I will overturn, overturn, overturn it, and it ſhall be no more, until he comes whoſe right it is, and I will give it him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Thought it not unſeaſonable (being deſir'd) to explain this Text, which (as it is credibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) was intended by the Popiſh Faction to Conſummate and Cloak the horrible malice of their Bloody Conſpiracy againſt the Life of his moſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47158:4"/> Sacred Majeſty; but conceiv'd it uſeful and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to apply it to whom moſt properly it appertains, as well for the juſtifying of his Royal Perſon, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of all honeſt Proteſtants, as alſo for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof and Conviction of our Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed to handle this Text with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mind, faithful love to Truth, and due regard to the Teſtimonies of the Holy Scriptures, with the ſenſe of the firſt General Councils, and the Doctrine of the Fathers in the firſt five or ſix hundred years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt; whereby you may evidently perceive, and be fully ſatisfied, that the King, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> who hold the true Apoſtolick Faith, and bind themſelves by Mutual Oaths to uphold and maintain the ſame, are not ſentenced with the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Curſe of God, as was denounced againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but that the Antichriſtian Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Man of Sin, now of a long time reveal'd, with all his bloody and Idolatrous Train; the <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Tribe have their Judgment denounc'd in the New Teſtament, which lingreth not, and their Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſlumbereth not.</p>
            <p>I obſerve with S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> not the <hi>Monk;</hi> that all Holy Writ is ſo tempered by the Holy Ghoſt, that <hi>quod alibi obſcurius, alibi clarius explicitur,</hi> one porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scripture explains another; and that is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all the Orthodox to be the moſt certain and undoubted Expoſition. Wherefore that this Text may be rightly underſtood, the Matter therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained muſt, for it requires it, be conſulted of in our Bibles in the following particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47158:4"/>
               <item>I. The Time when this Prophecy was declar'd.</item>
               <item>II. The Cauſes wherefore this Prophecy was declar'd.</item>
               <item>III. The Event, being a dreadful Curſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Wherein obſerve,</head>
                     <item>1. The Authority, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Charge, <hi>Thou wicked and prophane.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The Parties, <hi>Prince and People.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. The Confuſion, <hi>I'll overturn, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. The Duration, <hi>Until he comes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>IV. The Promiſe annex'd.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Wherein obſerve,</head>
                     <item>1. The Kingdom of Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>He comes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. His Claim, <hi>Whoſe right it is.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Divine Inſtitution, <hi>I will give it him.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of all theſe in order, by Gods aſſiſtance, with Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences from, and Application to the whole matter, I ſhall conclude with the uſes proper for our ſelves to make of it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, of the <hi>Time when.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The Time when this Prophecy was made, is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily known, when we look upon <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3. where the Prophet gives the World to underſtand expreſly the Year, the Month, and the Day, the Word of the Lord came unto him; <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it came to paſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the fourth month, in the fifth day of the month, which was the fifth year of King</hi> Jehoiakin's <hi>Captivity, the Word of the Lord came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47158:5"/> Ezekiel <hi>the Prieſt, in the Land of the</hi> Caldeans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Compare this with 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 24. 15, 16, &amp; 17. verſes, and there you ſhall find that this King <hi>Jehoiakin,</hi> the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> was carried away to <hi>Babylon</hi> in the eighth year of his Reign, and the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> made <hi>Mattaniah</hi> his Fathers Brother King in his ſtead, and changed his name to <hi>Zedekiah:</hi> inſomuch that by theſe places of Scripture it evidently appears, that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> began to prophecy much upon the midſt of King <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s Reign, for he reigned eleven years. For by that you ſee, that the fifth of <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin</hi>'s Captivity muſt be the fifth of <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s Reign. The Text calls this time, <hi>Iniquitas Termini,</hi> by an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallage,</hi> for <hi>Terminus Iniquitatis,</hi> when Iniquity ſhall have an end; that is, now is the time come that all the revolt, and back-ſlidings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by Idolatry, Blood-ſhed, and Prophaneneſs, is come to remembrance, and it ſhall now end in <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s days, who ſhall with the people be carried Captive unto <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The Cauſes wherefore this Sentence was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd are twofold; the firſt, is the provocations of the people moving and incenſing Gods wrath againſt them; and to this relates the firſt verſe of the Text, which ſaith, <hi>you have made your iniquity to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred:</hi> and in the 23. verſe next before the Text, it is ſaid, <hi>But he will call to remembrance the iniquity;</hi> which according to the Original may be well tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, <hi>Hereby you call to remembrance,</hi> that is, by this contempt and diſdain which you caſt upon my Word in the mouth of my Prophet, which ſeemeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47158:5"/> to you as a falſe divination, ver. 23. you do provoke me to call to remembrance all your wickedneſs, and the iniquity of your forefathers, for this obduration of heart againſt my Meſſenger, and breach of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhews what you are: ver. 24. <hi>So that in all your doings your ſins do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, becauſe, I ſay, that you are come to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance;</hi> that is, by this your hardneſs of heart, and contempt of the Prophets Doctrine, you force me, ſaith the Lord, to remember your Idolatry, Bloodſhed, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, and Apoſtaſies in all kinds; all which the Prophet ſets down in the next Chapter, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>2. The ſecond Cauſe here mentioned is God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, and expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>Ye ſhall be taken with the hand;</hi> which ſeems, as if it were, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Cauſe, but indeed the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> was the Inſtrumental Cauſe of their Captivity, to whoſe hands God delivered them up: In the 23. ver. it is, <hi>Ye ſhall be taken with the hand;</hi> and in the 11th ver. before the Text, it is call'd, <hi>The Hand of the Slayer;</hi> and in the 9th and 10th verſes it is ſet forth with much fierceneſs, <hi>A Sword, a Sword is ſharpned, and alſo furbiſhed, it is furbiſhed to make a ſore ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> by this Sword ſharpned and furbiſhed, being an evident ſign of Gods Wrath, is ſignified, that he was incens'd to a very great height of fierceneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and that appears by the effects and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence it had upon them, in the 7th ver. <hi>Every heart ſhall melt, and all hands ſhall be feeble, and every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall be faint, and all knees ſhall be weak as water.</hi> Alas! alas! when the point of Gods Sword is ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47158:6"/> the Gates, what hearts can endure, or hands be ſtrong to deal with it, or in any way be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it? Thus we ſee what's the ſad and dreadful cauſe of mens Confuſions, even Gods ſevere anger, ſo highly provok'd with repeated contempts, and hardneſs of heart againſt his Meſſengers and Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſent ſo ſedulouſly to inſtruct them; and by the Inſtrumental Cauſe of this peoples calamity, the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> we alſo ſee, that it often comes to paſs, through the anger of the Lord againſt his own choſen people, he maketh uſe of, and ſtirreth up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them the hands and hearts of Heathen and prophane people.</p>
            <p>3. The third thing to be conſidered in the Text is the <hi>Event; i. e.</hi> the Sentence of Deſtruction de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, wherein we muſt obſerve theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>1. The Authority of it in ver. 20. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> What I ſay and denounce againſt this Prince, I have Gods Warrant for it, ſaith the Prophet, and that's the reaſon why he omits all terms of honour to this Prince; and I think he might have inlarg'd thus, and ſay, I know the Commandment of God in the Law concerning Princes, <hi>Ex. 22. 8. Thou ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the Gods, nor curſe the Rulers of thy people, for by God Kings do reign, and Princes do decree Juſtice:</hi> And that <hi>Solomon</hi> had taught, ſaying, <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought, for his unſearchable heart is in the hand of the Lord.</hi> And Kings are the Lords Anointed, ordain'd for our Nurſing Fathers, and therefore not to be touch'd with any violence: But I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47158:6"/> am commanded by the Hand of God upon me, and the Inſpiration of his Spirit within me, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord:</hi> as <hi>Saul</hi> told <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> told <hi>Ahab</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo I by the Word of the Lord, or the Lord by me, and my mouth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth, and ſaith thus againſt this Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>2. The Charge in this Sentence is obſervable, <hi>Thou prophane, wicked.</hi> You ſhall ſee theſe words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd in <hi>Jer.</hi> 52. 1, 2, 3. where <hi>Zedekiah</hi> is ſaid to do that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all that <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> had done: and <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin</hi>'s Charge you will find in <hi>Jer.</hi> 22. 17. he was tax'd for Idolatry, and ſhedding of Innocent blood, by offering up Children unto <hi>Moloch,</hi> for oppreſſion and violence, covetouſneſs, and prophaning holy things. And this was not ſpoken of him alone, but of all the people, and of the former Ages, ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, in the 4th Chap. of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4, 5. ver. the Prophet was to bear the iniquity of the people for 390 days, repreſenting all the years, a day for a year, down from <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> which time is computed by the Learned to be 390 years to the Captivity under <hi>Zedekiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. The Parties charged, <hi>Prince and People;</hi> the Prince was <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> whoſe name had been <hi>Matta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi> as is ſhew'd before, who now rebels againſt the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that had ſhew'd kindneſs, and made him King inſtead of <hi>Jehoiakin:</hi> the People are alſo concern'd here; for when it is ſaid, <hi>Remove the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, and take away the Crown;</hi> by the Diadem and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47158:7"/> Crown is meant the Government and Kingdom, the whole Nation; the <hi>Cidarin</hi> and <hi>Corona</hi> are Royal Ornaments; and by the ſigns <hi>Synechdochically,</hi> is meant the things ſignified, <hi>amove, tolle, i. e.</hi> Prophecy that the King and People ſhall be removed, and carried captive into <hi>Babylon; Haec non haec,</hi> this ſhall not be the ſame; <hi>i. e.</hi> this ſhall remain no more ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Nation.</p>
            <p>4. The Confuſion or Deſtruction denounced is to be conſidered, which is ſet forth in ſeveral expreſſions in the Text; as firſt, <hi>Exalt him that is low,</hi> that is, <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> who is now low in Captivity at <hi>Babylon,</hi> he ſhall be exalted; which came to paſs in the 37th year of his Captivity; 2 <hi>King. 25. 27, 28. &amp;c.</hi> you may read how <hi>Evilmerodach,</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up his head, and ſpake kindly unto him, and gave him an allowance a daily rate, for every day all the days of his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abaſe him that is high;</hi> that is, <hi>Zedekiah</hi> that is high-minded, and through the pride of his heart, and Gods anger, rebelleth againſt the King of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> ſhall be abaſed: this ungrateful, undutiful, and diſloyal Prince, requites the kindneſs, favours, and great honours conferr'd upon him by the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> with Conſpiracies, Plots, and Rebellion, 2 <hi>Kin. 24. ult.</hi> therefore abaſe him, caſt him off: <hi>I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected him, ſaith the Lord;</hi> which came to paſs you ſee in 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 25. The City was beſieged to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth year of King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and the City was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, and all the Men of War fled by night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was taken, and brought to the King of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47158:7"/> 
               <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Riblah,</hi> and he gave Judgment upon him, and bound him in Fetters of Braſs, and ſlew his Sons before his eyes, and put out his own eyes, and brought him to <hi>Babylon.</hi> The next words declaring this great Confuſion, are,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will overturn, overturn it, and it ſhall be no more;</hi> that is, with repeated Calamities and Judgments will I deſtroy it, with Sword, Famine, and Peſtilence; my accuſtomed and uſually ſent Judgments, I will bring it once, twice, and the third time, to make a full end of it, and it ſhall be no more; that is, not ſuch a great, terrible, and glorious people any more. This was fulfilled, you ſhall ſee that <hi>Nebuzaradan,</hi> Captain of the Guard, a Servant of the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> came to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and burnt the Houſe of the Lord, and the Houſe of the King, and all the Houſes of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and every Great Mans Houſe burnt he with fire, and broke the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and carried the reſt of the people away. And although by the Edict of <hi>Cyrus</hi> they had Laws after the City and the Temple was rebuilt, yet all was but ſlender and unſtable, as by the Hiſtory of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Eſrah</hi> doth appear; and ſince Chriſt came, whom they crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by the juſt Judgment of God upon them, they were utterly aboliſhed by <hi>Titus Veſpaſianus,</hi> and now are become the moſt diſtreſſed and deſpicable people, and Nation in the World.</p>
            <p>5. The Duration of this Judgment and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>until he comes:</hi> Here is a comfort promis'd them by the coming of Chriſt, which although that blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, hath happen'd unto them for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47158:8"/> a time that they could not receive the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> when he came, yet there's a time and a promiſe for their Reſtoration; upon this Promiſe, and other-like Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of Scripture, do they to this day depend, and look for the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to deliver them: and herein they are more happy than Antichriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, for there's not one ſyllable of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made for his reſtoring to the Truth which he hath forſaken, but he is to be conſum'd for ever by the Spirit of Gods Mouth, and utterly deſtroy'd by the brightneſs of his coming.</p>
            <p>4. The fourth particular, obſervable in the Text, is the promiſe of Chriſts coming; <hi>He comes, whoſe right it is, and I will give it him:</hi> Here's meant no Temporal Prince, but the coming of the ſame that was a long time before ſpoken of by the Kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Thou haſt made him little lower than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and haſt crowned him with Glory and Honour, thou haſt made him have Dominion over the works of thy hands, thou haſt put all things under his feet;</hi> and to the ſame Prince and perſons coming doth <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> ſpeak: <hi>He cometh ſuddenly to his Temple; Behold he ſhall come,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and who may abide his coming?</hi> therefore it is ſaid by S. <hi>Paul, he was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heir of all things: He comes,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>whoſe right it is Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth <hi>King of the</hi> Jews. This right of Ruling and Power, the Lord Jeſus ſaith of himſelf in <hi>Mat. 28. 18. All power is given me of my Father in Heaven, and in Earth;</hi> therefore it is ſaid in the Text <hi>I will give it him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Text thus open'd, and the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47158:8"/> thereof conſidered, there do ariſe theſe ſeveral Inferences.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Inference is from the Time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>When the Wicked plot againſt the Juſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine in rebellious Conſpiracies, then doth approach the appointed ruine of the Plotters. This Sin of Witchcraft carries men blind-folded to deſtruction, and that is the reaſon, I think, why it is ſo called; men are bewitch'd to lay Snares that their own feet may be taken. <hi>Non eſt Lex aequior ulla, quam necit artifices arte perire ſuae.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>A juſter Law can no man make, nor wiſh,</l>
                  <l>Than Plotters of Death ſhould for Plotting periſh.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Therefore did the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſing, <hi>The Heathen are ſunk in the Pit that they have made, in the Net which they have hid, are their own feet taken:</hi> And from this time of <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s Rebellion, when he conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and brought upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Plotting a total Ruine, we may very well obſerve, that Conſpiring and Plotting Times are but the Fore-noons to the Evenings of executing Rebels: I have a very ſure word of teſtimony for it, <hi>Pſal. 37. 12, 13. The wicked plotteth againſt the juſt, and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt him with his teeth, but the Lord laugheth at him to ſcorn, for he knoweth that his day is coming.</hi> The Lord laugheth to ſcorn at the wicked Plots and Conſpiracies of bewitch'd minds, and though men do not perceive their approaching Ruine, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that his day is coming: In the Net which every
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47158:9"/> bloody Traytor hath made, may his own foot be firſt taken. And do not we now ſee whoſe days are come, and whoſe iniquity will have an end? is it not the days of ſuch as deviſe Rebellion? and who hath not a full ſenſe of theſe unquiet and reſtleſs Spirits, who never ceaſe to plot againſt the juſt, yea a moſt juſt, tender, and gracious Soveraign; and who are thoſe, and how many of all hands do we daily ſee, that gnaſh their teeth againſt him, and againſt his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church and Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Tribe, the Brood of lame <hi>Loyolah,</hi> falſly call'd <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> for indeed they are <hi>aes avitae,</hi> ſaith one, ſpend all their time and wits to bring the Kings of the Earth to the Battel of the great day of the Lord, that is, to ſow Sedition and Rebellion in the whole World; witneſs their late Diſmal Plot of <hi>Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and this now diſcover'd of no leſs danger, as 'tis credibly reported: Dr. <hi>Hall</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> obſerves the time of this plotting Confederacy, with their ador'd Idol the Pope, to be approaching, ſaying, <q rend="inline">All the World knows how that pretended Chair of <hi>Peter</hi> tottered and crack'd, threatens a ſpeedy ruine to her Uſurper: how is it that it ſtill ſtands?</q> This rebellious <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah (Jer.</hi> 52. 1, 2, 3. and 2 <hi>King.</hi> 24. 18, 19, 20. which two places of Scripture, are the ſame word by word) felt the revengeful ſtroke of Gods hand of Juſtice, in a ſhort time, after his ungrateful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful oppoſing of the King of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking of Antichriſt (who indeed is a Rebel againſt Chriſt, profeſſing the name of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47158:9"/> but oppoſing him in Doctrine and Practice) tells us, <hi>his deſtruction is ſwift, and his judgment lingereth not.</hi> And to conclude this point, ſee how free from this witchcraft of Rebellion all the true Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Princes and People are, and ever have been accounted, inſomuch that their perfect Loyalty, and true obſervance of their Kings, is born as a mark in their Forehead, and is become a Proverb, <hi>No Biſhop, no King; no King, no Biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. Inference from the Provocation.</head>
               <p>When obdurate hearts contemn the words of God, admoniſhing and threatning by his Meſſengers, they aggravate their former ſins, and exaſperate Divine Indignation againſt them. In the verſe before the Text, <hi>Hoc revocatis, i. e.</hi> hereby ye call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that is, by diſdaining my Prophets and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, which in your ſight is as a falſe Divination, through the hardneſs of your hearts againſt me, ſaith the Lord, you provoke me to call to mind the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, prophaneneſs, idolatries, bloodſhed, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and blaſphemies that is amongſt you, and all the Apoſtacy of your Forefathers this 380 years and upwards. <hi>You have tranſgreſſed very much,</hi> 2 Chron. 36. 14, 15. <hi>after all the abomination of the Heathen, and polluted the Houſe of the Lord; and I ſent unto you my Meſſengers, riſing up betimes, and ſending, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had compaſſion on you,</hi> ſaith the Lord. But this is it that imbittered me againſt you more than any thing, <hi>you have mocked my Meſſengers, and deſpiſed my words, till my wruth roſe againſt you, till there was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47158:10"/> no remedy.</hi> Pro. 29. 1. <hi>He that being often reproved, hardneth his neck, ſhall be ſuddenly deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</hi> This was the caſe of <hi>Ely</hi>'s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who diſdaining the voice of their Father, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in their pollutions, till God in his wrath ſlew them: This hardning of the heart, is nothing elſe but the contempt of Gods Word; and the contempt of Gods Word, is the provoking of God to his face. When the people invited to the Wedding, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Marriage-Supper, made light of their call, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the King heard thereof, he was wroth, and ſent forth his Armies, and deſtroyed thoſe Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and burnt up their City. It is ſtrange to ſee with what a ſcornful ſtate the proud ambitious Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Chair of <hi>Peter</hi> would trample upon the Necks of all his Brethren, and how he looks from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft upon the honeſt Proteſtants reproving him, he looks upon them far below him, and with ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous looks deſpiſeth them; for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies. Thus he, and all his Train of the Scarlet Conclave, the Cardinals, with the ſly Jeſuite (think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves righteous, deſpiſing others, as the Spirit of God rebuketh them, <hi>Luc.</hi> 18. 9.) do aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate their former Revolt and Apoſtacy this thouſand years ſtanding, and call all to remembrance, that at laſt they ſhall, through the fire of Gods wrath, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by incens'd, <hi>be taken with the hand,</hi> as the Text ſpeaks. But as for the meekneſs and humility of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and our readineſs to condeſcend and ſubmit to the Truth, let the World be our Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as learned Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> declares it; <q rend="inline">If any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47158:10"/> learned man of our Adverſaries, or of all the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that be alive, be able to bring any one ſufficient Sentence, or Teſtimony, out of any old Doctor, or Father, or out of any old General Council, or out of the holy Scriptures of God, or any one Example of the Primitive Church, whereby it may be clearly and plainly proved, that there was any private Maſs, or that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was delegated for Univerſal and Supreme Head of the Catholick Church, with Invocation upon Saints, worſhipping of Images, and buying of Indulgences and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons; or that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was accounted and call'd the Univerſal and Catholick Church, or any thing own'd as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> at that time, for the ſpace of ſix hundred years after Chriſt, we are content to yield, and to ſubſcribe, otherwiſe we hold our ſelves ſtrictly obliged to retain the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Faith of Chriſt which we do now profeſs, and as it is now by our Laws eſtabliſhed.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Inference the third, from God provoked, <hi>Ye ſhall be taken with the hand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Idolatry, Bloodſhed, Oppreſſion, Prophaneneſs and Blaſphemy, are the crying ſins that provoke God ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and haſten his unavoidable Judgments ſooneſt. In <hi>Ezek. 22. 3. The City maketh Idols againſt her ſelf, to defile her ſelf.</hi> Idolatry is an open defiance to the Deity, therefore abhorr'd of God above other ſins, and call'd by Gods Spirit, <hi>the Abomination;</hi> and therefore it is ſaid in the Text, v. 24. <hi>Becauſe you have made your iniquity to be remembred;</hi> this was ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it was the cauſe that made other ſins to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47158:11"/> remembred; and for Bloodſhed and Idolatry, being put together, it is expreſly declar'd by the Prophet, Chap. 22. 4. that they have haſten'd their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>And thou haſt become,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>guilty in thy blood which thou haſt ſhed, and haſt defiled thy ſelf with thine Idols which thou haſt made, and thou haſt cauſed thy days to draw near.</hi> And as to their oppreſſion, prophaneneſs and blaſphemy, it is declared in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. to be ſo notorious and palpable, that God blew the fire of his wrath to conſume them: Their ſins did teſtifie againſt them, the way of peace they knew not, truth was fallen in their ſtreets, and equity could not enter; and <hi>Eſay</hi> crys out, that he won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred there was no Interceſſor, <hi>Eſ. 59. 16. Eſay, Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſpend their breath and their books in declaring the falling away of theſe people from God, and his worſhip; inſomuch that at laſt you ſee the fierce anger, wrath and indignation of God fell upon them, in this King <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4. Inference from the Charge, <hi>Thou wicked and prophane Prince,</hi> is this:</head>
               <p>It is ſuch as revolt from the Faith, deſpiſing holy things, and fall to the practiſes of the Heathen World, that the Scriptures call wicked and prophane, and never charge any ſo that keep the true Faith and Worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>Theſe people were juſtly charged, and their Prince alſo, as wicked and prophane, and that for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: (1.) They had forſaken the Lord and his Law, which is declar'd by good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> in 2 <hi>King. 22. 13. Our Fathers hearken'd not unto the words of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47158:11"/> Book,</hi> (meaning the Book of the Law found by <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> in the Houſe of the Lord) <hi>to do according to all that is written concerning us.</hi> And this falling away from Gods Law, the Scripture calls <hi>Fornication,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring theſe people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſordid men, <hi>Ezek. 16. 15. Thou playedſt the Harlot, and poureſt out thy fornications on every one that paſſed by.</hi> (2.) They deſpis'd the holy things of the Lord: <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> built Altars for <hi>Baal</hi> in the Houſe of the Lord, and ſet a graven Image, of the Grove which he had made, in the Houſe, of which the Lord had ſaid, <hi>In this Houſe will I put my Name for ever:</hi> Therefore doth <hi>Ezek.</hi> Chap. 22. 8. cry out againſt them, <hi>Thou haſt deſpiſed my holy things, and haſt prophaned my Sabbaths.</hi> And ver. 26. <hi>Her Prieſts have violated my Law, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned my holy things: I am prophaned among them.</hi> (3.) Theſe people were juſtly called wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, for they follow'd the Idolatrous practiſes of the Heathen World; <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did as <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> had done, and <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> as <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> his Predeceſſor, and he did as <hi>Jehoahaz, and he did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that his Fathers</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>and</hi> Ahab <hi>had done.</hi> Now <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> built up the High-places, rear'd up Altars for <hi>Baal,</hi> made a Grove, and worſhipped the Sun, and the Moon, and the Planets, and all the Hoſt of Heaven. (4.) They delivered their Children to paſs through the fire to <hi>Moloch</hi> at <hi>Topheth,</hi> and ſhed Innocent blood: And <hi>behold,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>the Princes of</hi> Iſrael <hi>every one were in thee to their power to ſhed innocent blood, like ravening Wolves to deſtroy Souls for diſhoneſt gain,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47158:12"/> Ezek.</hi> 22. 27. Theſe Abominations were grounds e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to charge them, as the Prophet doth here, <hi>Thou wicked and prophane:</hi> And beſides all theſe, there did Oppreſſion and Uſury, Lewdneſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, reign in the higheſt degree amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Now having ſeen who the Scriptures call wicked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Old Teſtament, it lies upon us to know who are ſo charged alſo in the New Teſtament, and for what; and that appears plainly, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 7, 8, 10. S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells you, <hi>He who now letteth, will let, until he be taken out of the way, and then ſhall that wicked be revealed, i. e.</hi> He that letteth and oppoſeth Chriſts Doctrine and Kingdom, is that wicked one, which in his appointed time ſhall be reveal'd, and in the 10th verſe he gives the reaſon why he calls him wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Becauſe they received not the love of the Truth.</hi> This is much like that of Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Haman,</hi> who had conſpir'd to deſtroy all the Inheritance of God, the Generation of the <hi>Jews.</hi> This Adverſary and Enemy is that wicked <hi>Haman:</hi> So in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 12. we find that the Church of Chriſt under the New Teſtament, <hi>wreſtleſs againſt Powers and Principalities,</hi> that is, men exerciſing Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which he calls <hi>ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, in the 16th verſe he tells you, that you are to take the Shield of Faith, which is able to quench all the fiery darts of the Wicked; whereby you muſt underſtand; that that wicked one hath fiery Darts with him to throw at the faithful, and by fiery Darts you can think of nothing elſe but bloody Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47158:12"/> And laſtly, you may know that wicked party by his blaſphemy, prophaneneſs, and coming after the working of Satan, with all Powers, and Signs, and lying Wonders, who oppoſing and exalting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; <hi>ſo that he as God ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> So that in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, when theſe are compared with the former Prince and People, they are guilty of the ſame wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and prophaneneſs: As thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <list>
                              <head>Under the Old Teſtament.</head>
                              <item>1. Thoſe forſook the Law of the Lord.</item>
                              <item>2. Thoſe deſpiſed holy things.</item>
                              <item>3. Thoſe followed the Idolatrous Practiſes of the Heathen World.</item>
                              <item>4. Thoſe deliver'd their Children to <hi>Maloch,</hi> and ſhed Innocent Blood.</item>
                              <item>To <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the Text it is ſaid, <hi>Thou prophane, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <list>
                              <head>Under the New Teſtament</head>
                              <item>1. Theſe received not the love of the Truth.</item>
                              <item>2. Theſe ſitting in the Temple of God, ſhew himſelf that he is God.</item>
                              <item>3. Theſe exalt above God, with ſigns and lying wonders, after the working of Satan.</item>
                              <item>4. Theſe ſhoot Fiery Darts of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
                              <item>To Antichriſt and his Kingdom in the New Teſtament, <hi>Thou man of ſin, and wicked,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 3. 8.</item>
                           </list>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:47158:13"/>
               <p>Now I will ſhew you how the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church reſemble revolted <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their Apoſtacy and wickedneſs; and will alſo declare how clear and free the King and Church of <hi>England</hi> are from this Charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polanus</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Canons and Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, with the Lives and Practiſes of the Popes, do expreſly declare them to be Antichriſt; and Anti-Chriſt is defin'd to be a Man exerciſing Authority, Head of the Univerſal Apoſtacy, and Deſertion of the Faith, profeſſing the Name of Chriſt, yet op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing himſelf to Chriſt and his Doctrine. That he is a Man exerciſing Authority no Man denys, that he is Head of Univerſal Apoſtacy, and oppoſeth Chriſt and his Doctrine, I will plainly ſhew in my Application. We are oblig'd to regard his Perſon as a Prince and a Prelate by the Laws of God and Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> to give honour to whom honour is due; but it is his Vices and Corruption we cry out againſt, and what the Scripture and judicious Divines, ancient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, of reformed Proteſtants have declar'd concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, we may without malice, or hatred ſpeak of him; and omitting all terms of honour, he is an Idolater, a Hypocriſe, a Blaſphemer, ambitious, proud, lawleſs, and forbidding to marry, covetous, vain, a Lyar, a cruel Tyrant, a Perſecutor, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of the Saints, deſpiſing holy things, and ſitting in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</p>
               <p>The Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Pope as Supreme Head of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47158:13"/> Church, and Images, with the Relicks of Saints, and their Invocations upon the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> with the lifting up of the Hoſt are as directly againſt the I. and II. Commandment, as Blood ſhed is againſt the VI. and as palpable as it was with <hi>Iſrael</hi> who worſhipp'd the Sun, Moon, and Planets; <hi>He muſt have a good Hide,</hi> ſaith Dr. Hall, <hi>that can worſhip</hi> Martin'<hi>s Boots,</hi> George'<hi>s Scabbard,</hi> Criſpin'<hi>s Pareing-Knife,</hi> Thomaſes <hi>her Shoo, and</hi> Joſeph's <hi>Breeches;</hi> to equalize theſe Fopperies with the Son of God in point of worſhip, as thoſe do who fall before them, and call upon them, as <hi>Eraeſmus</hi> complains, is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Idolatry, and horrible Impiety.</p>
               <p>The Blood-ſhed of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo ſenſibly known through all the Chriſtian World that every Country can bear witneſs to it, and no marvel the Holy Ghoſt compare her to a Woman clothed in Scarlet, and drunk with the Blood of Saints.</p>
               <p>The fiery Darts of this wicked-one have been ſo prevalent in <hi>Italy,</hi> that at one time was condemn'd 16000 Proteſtants, where 18 had their Throats and jugular Veins cut with a Butchers-Knife, the Butcher putting it between his Teeth whilſt he did rid his Hand of one and take the other. In Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days were ſeveral hundreds, here in <hi>England,</hi> burnt, in the ſpace of the two laſt years of her Reign, 13 ſometimes together, 12. 10. 6. 5. and other numbers, Biſhops, Preachers, Gentlemen, Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, old and blind Men, Cripples, and poor Maids; no ſort of Chriſtians could eſcape the fury of theſe bloody Perſecutions.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:47158:14"/>
               <p>And to ſpeak of their Covetouſneſs, Oppreſſion, Prophaneneſs, and Blaſphemies which are ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, will be too tedious for me to hint here in the corner of a Sermon; therefore, in a word, I leave this point concerning the charge, and ſay it may be well ſaid, <hi>Thou wicked and prophane Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>whoſe Day is come, and thy Iniquity ſhall have an end; remove the Diadem, take away the Crown; I will exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high; I will overturn, overturn, overturn it, until he comes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Inference the fifth, from the Confuſion of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Crowns and Kingdoms cannot ſtand, when God Almighty hath denounc'd their fall: Witneſs the fall of all the mighty Monarchs of the World, and therefore this Prophet expoſtulateth pathetically, <hi>Can thy Heart endure, or will thy Hands be strong, in the day that I ſhall deal with thee; I will overturn, overturn, overturn it, and it ſhall be no more; and who can ſay to God, What doſt thou: The Beaſt with ſeven Heads and ten Crowns muſt fall and tumble down, when God is pleas'd to toſs them. Whom the Lord ſhall deſtroy with the Spirit of his Mouth, and conſume with the brightneſs of his coming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as for the King and Church of <hi>England,</hi> being free from the Charge, they may be alſo concluded to be free from the Judgment, in the ſence of all cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable minds.</p>
               <p>And that they are free from the Charge, let every ſober-minded Man weigh theſe Particulars.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47158:14"/>
               <p>1. The King and the Church of <hi>England</hi> proteſt to maintain, nor ſuffer for no other Faith, but that which was once by Apoſtolical Tradition deliver'd to the Saints: This Profeſſion do both Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by a mutual Oath and Covenant, bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to aſſert, keep, and uphold, to the honour and glory of God; as good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> and his People, in their days. His Majeſty, (as other Kings his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, of bleſſed memory, at their Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) firſt promiſeth (being ask'd by the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops) to keep, and afterwards by Oath confirms, the Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England;</hi> namely, the Laws, Cuſtoms, and Franchiſes, granted to the Clergie by the glorious King St. <hi>Edward</hi> his Predeceſſor, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Laws of God, the true Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and according to the Prerogatives of the Kings thereof, and defend and uphold the ſame to the honour of God, as much as in him lyeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Oath.</label>
                  <hi>The things that I have here promis'd, I ſhall perform and keep, ſo help me God, and the Contents of this Book.</hi> This Oath is publiſhed in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr's Anſwer to a Remonſtrance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the 26th of <hi>May</hi> 1642.</p>
               <p>The ſame Oath, for matter, you may find in an old Manuſcript, containing the Form of Coronation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the publick Library at <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not this as firm, and as great a Covenant as bleſſed King <hi>Joſiah</hi> made, who ſtood by a Pillar, and made a Covenant before the Lord, to walk after the Lord, and to keep his Commandments, and his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47158:15"/> and his Statutes, with all their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all the People ſtood to the Covenant, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23. 3.</p>
               <p>So all the People of <hi>England,</hi> and all his Majeſty's Subjects, bind themſelves ſtrictly by two Oaths, called the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> to obey the King's Laws in all true Faith and Allegiance, renouncing all Forreign Powers, and declaring the King's Majeſty Supreme Head and Governour in all matters, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Temporal, next under Chriſt, in all theſe His Majeſty's Dominions: Thus do both Prince and People moſt unanimouſly, and faithfully, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to ſtick to the Profeſſion of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as it is by Law eſtabliſh'd, being no other than the ſame as chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, and the pure Times of the Primitive Church maintained in the firſt Centuries after Chriſt.</p>
               <p>2. For the purity, juſtneſs, and reaſonableneſs of His Majeſty's Laws whereby we are Govern'd, the Common, Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical; all the malice of our Adverſaries cannot impeach them of the leaſt ſavour of Idolatry, or Impiety, Prophaneneſs, or Blaſphemies, as thoſe of rebellious <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Old did, and of the <hi>Roman Papiſts</hi> under the New Teſtament do: The Common-Law being certain reaſonable Cuſtoms refined by ſucceeding Ages, and gathered out of Divine, Natural, and Moral Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; our Civil and Canon-Laws, being all grounded upon the Word of God, and the Decrees of General Councils, and the Sence of the Fathers in the firſt ſix-hundred years after Chriſt; and in this it is as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47158:15"/> clear as the Sun at Noon-day, that neither His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, nor his People can be charg'd for wickedneſs, nor prophaneneſs, in their Profeſſion, nor Laws.</p>
               <p>3. For the Doctrine which we reach it is briefly contain'd in the Creed, call'd the Apoſtles Creed, the Lords-Prayer, and Ten Commandments, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd throughout the whole Bible: we believe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, we pray for nothing, and we practice no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as neceſſary to Salvation, but what is plainly prov'd by evident Scriptures. And as for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Diſcipline, and Worſhip of our Church, it is acknowledg'd by all Judicious Proteſtants to be the beſt conſtituted Church this day in the whole World, and that in the main, the Doctrine, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Worſhip, being ſo decently and excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fram'd for edification, that it makes all Men that duly obſerve it, truly and ſoberly religious, ſecuring them (as a Reverend Divine ſaith) on the one ſide from the wild Freaks of Enthuſiaſm, and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the groſs Follies of Superſtition.</p>
               <p>4. As for any violence and cruelty, we thank God, the World is our Witneſs, we can waſh our Hands in Innocence; none condemn'd to death for bare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in point of Conſcience, or different Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of Religion. It is Fellons and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, becauſe they have not the fear of God before their Eyes, by the King's Law do dye. His moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty being of that gracious and Lamb-like Diſpoſition, that he laboureth rather through ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to regain, than through ſeverity to compell Diſſenters, to Unity of Spirit and Uniformity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:47158:16"/>
               <p>5. And laſtly, weigh our Practices, I mean the Lives and Converſations of thoſe that are true Sons, and Obſervers of the Church: we ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that through our careleſneſs, and want of more ſtrictneſs, in many things we do offend all; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, at our daily and publick, as well as private De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, we pray for true repentance, and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and there's not a Chriſtian Man that hath a little Grain of Charity in him, that will deny, but that we through a certain (though not ſo Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal as wiſh'd) Obedience, receive, and ſubmit to the Truth, Will, Law, and Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>To theſe things, if I had time to amplifie, I would, nor do, deſire no more Credit than ſhall be due to the fair Evidence of clear Scripture, and ſound Reaſon, the two Maſter Pillars of a good Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Now upon theſe and other like grounds, is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the unmovable ſettled ends of our fixed hopes through Faith in our dear Saviour, that we are not Sentenc'd with Idolatrous <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Law, are not, nor ſhall be condemn'd with Antichriſtian <hi>Popery</hi> under the Goſpel: And I conclude this Point with that of our Saviour, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 27. Confiding that it is appertaining to us, as much as to any other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church in the World; for ſome have called the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, the <hi>Primogenita</hi> of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and for certain it is a Member of the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and therefore may expect her Share in the Legacy of Chriſt; <hi>Peace I leave with you, Peace I give unto you, not as the World gives give I unto you,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47158:16"/> therefore let not your Heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.</hi> And this leads me to the next Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sixthly, The ſixth Inference is from Chriſt's coming.</head>
               <p>The Lord's goodneſs is ſo far extended to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Spouſe, the true Church Catholick, and to every Member thereof, that in the greateſt diſtreſs and confuſions in the World, Chriſt and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts will attend the faithful; <hi>Job</hi> 5. 19, 20, 21, &amp;c. <hi>He will deliver thee in ſix troubles, and in ſeven there ſhall no evil touch thee; in Famine he ſhall redeem thee from Death, and in War from the power of the Sword; thou ſhalt be hid from the Scourge of the Tongue, neither ſhalt thou be afraid of Destruction when it cometh.</hi> What unſpeakable comforts, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and rejoycing all the holy Martyrs of Jeſus have ever had in their ſufferings, will be too long to relate here: <hi>He comes whoſe right it is, and I will give it him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think you do evidently perceive, and are fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, by theſe things already ſaid, concerning this Text, that there needs no further diſcourſe to make all Men apprehend, how free, and plainly unſpotted, with the Charge and Curſe here denounced againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the preſent State of <hi>England</hi> ſtands. The City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> were curs'd, mark, as you have heard, for breach of their Oath and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and further Rebellion (to the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> though a <hi>Pagan</hi> King) together with their Contempt of God's Word, Idolatrous, and Prophane
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47158:17"/> Practiſes; but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants are hated, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, accus'd, and perſecuted by the Popiſh Faction, for no other cauſe, more than for bearing true Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the rightful and lawful King of their Realm, and maintaining, as by Oath they are bound, that the Pope hath no power to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe of his Kingdoms; his preſent Majeſty, <hi>Charles</hi> the II. being the 26th that ſucceſſively in the right Line from the Conquerour have reign'd abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Kings of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> Now I will ſhew you, by way of Application, who have fallen off from the Faith under the New Teſtament, and that plainly and particularly in what points, and then you may judge whether the like Curſe, as was ſo dreadfully denounced againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> may not be alſo hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their heads, and pointing at their doors, being palpably guilty of the lille Charge.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Canonizing, as <hi>de fide,</hi> a new Doctrine, contrary to the Catholick Faith, for the firſt five or ſix hundred years after Chriſt, is become a falſe Church (or the Church of Antichriſt, which is no part of the true Church of Chriſt) but an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume, or a bad humour in the body, and no part of the body, I mean the true Spiritual and Myſtical Body of Chriſt: And as the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> fell off from the Worſhip of God, and ador'd the Golden Calfs made by <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and turn'd <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Houſe of God, into <hi>Bethaven,</hi> a Houſe of Iniquity, ſo have Papiſts turn'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which was once a pure flouriſhing Church, to a corrupt Den of Thieves. And yet it is granted by judicious Proteſtants, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47158:17"/> ſome may poſſibly be ſaved, though with great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, that are in Communion with her, and groan under the lewd and Antichriſtian Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices (impos'd by her as neceſſary to Salvation) which overthrow the Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, (although held by themſelves) and are contrary point-blank to the Catholick Faith once delivered to the Saints; particularly theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>1. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hold and affirm the Pope to be <hi>Univerſal and Supreme Head of the Catholick Church, Caput totius Eccleſiae Militantis;</hi> Univerſal Father of the Church, the only Diſpenſer of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Benedictions; thus dignified, he Lords it over all the Clergy upon Earth. Our Creed, compoſed by the Apoſtles, teacheth us to believe firſt in God the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord: and the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed explains it, I believe in one God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Scripture explains this plainly, in the 4th of <hi>Eph. 15. Speaking the truth in love, grow up into him in all things, which is the Head, even Chriſt:</hi> By which it appears we have no Univerſal Head for the Church Militant, but our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>2. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is held by them to be the Catholick Church, contrary to our Belief in our Creed, which ſaith, <hi>I believe in the holy Catholick Church;</hi> and explain'd in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, <hi>I believe in one Catholick and Apoſtolick Church:</hi> All the Elect of God that ever have been, now are, or ever ſhall be in the world, comprehending all particular Churches
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47158:18"/> which were before the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and were in the ſame time that ſhe flouriſhed, in other Provinces in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> and now are ſeparated from her, making up one Catholick Church, the Myſtical Body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>3. The Doctrine of the Popes Infallibility, that he cannot Err, and that his Authority confirm'd by Councils, is greater and more certain than the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, doth fly in the face of all the Foundation of our Faith; for we take, as the holy Catholick Church hath ever done, the holy Scriptures for the only cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rule of our Faith and Practice, from which we own no higher Authority to appeal unto, no, though an Angel did preach things contrary to the Scriptures, they are to us an <hi>Anathema;</hi> he, the Pope, can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence, they ſay, againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter;</hi> that is, controul and wreſt the ſenſe of the Scriptures writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> yea againſt the Old and New Teſtament he can, <hi>plenitudine poteſtatis,</hi> as much as God. This Doctrine you will find often boaſted of in their Canons and Decretals.</p>
               <p>4. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth plainly and point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blank oppoſe and overthrow the Catholick Faith, concerning the Remiſſion of ſins: The Apoſtles in the Creed, as all the New Teſtament moſt amply and largely explaineth, teach us to believe the forgiveneſs of ſins; and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth ſet it up on quite other terms, by propoſing that gift, I mean, the forgiveneſs of ſins, to be ſold by the Pope, and his Prieſts, if any will be ſo fondly blind as to buy in the vile Market of Indulgences; ſo, in a word, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47158:18"/> Faith is to believe the forgiveneſs of ſins, and the Doctrine of Popery is to ſell and buy it.</p>
               <p>5. The Popiſh Faction overthrow and utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found by their new Doctrine and Practice, the Faith and Practice of the Catholick Church in Prayer: Our Saviour Chriſt himſelf taught us to pray after this manner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> directing our Petitions to God the Father, by the help of the Holy Ghoſt, in the Name and by the Mediation of God the Son; ſo are all Prayers made in the Old and New Teſtament: But the Papiſts call upon Saints and Angels, and becauſe they believe it, for it is a prevailing Argument with them, that the Kingdom of Heaven is divided into two parts, the Kingdom of Mercy to the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the Kingdom of Juſtice to Chriſt; they pray more for mercy unto <hi>Mary,</hi> than unto God through Chriſt.</p>
               <p>6. They contradict and oppoſe the Chriſtian Faith in the firſt ſix hundred years, by the moſt unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Point to be impos'd for matter of belief as ever any man can hear of, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> come out of the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> under Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the III. He who contended with <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> They believe that the Bread and the Wine in the Lords Supper, after Conſecration, is ſubſtantially and materially changed, contrary to our Natural Senſe, Seeing, Taſting, and Feeling; and we believe it, that they are Signs and Symbols of a Spiritual Food, and refection which our Souls receive from Chriſts Body and Blood which was given for us.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being conſidered, every Chriſtian
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47158:19"/> man will ſay, that it was piouſly done of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany, Jerome</hi> in <hi>Prague, Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> in <hi>France, Wickliffe, Bilney</hi> and <hi>Tindal</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> to ſeparate from this Apoſtate Church, leſt they ſhould be partakers of her ſins, and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of her Plagues, <hi>Rev. 18. 4. Hoſ. 4. 15. 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 14. whoſe judgment now of a long time lingreth not, and her damnation ſlumbereth not. <hi>Rev. 13. Let him that underſtandeth count the number of the Beaſt.</hi> There's a ſet time appointed for his Judgment, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in 2 <hi>Theſ. 2. 7. until he be taken out of the way;</hi> as it is in the Text, <hi>until he comes.</hi> Let any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, unbyaſs'd ſpirited man weigh theſe Points and Scriptures before-recited, and he will ſoon reſolve himſelf how tottering the See of <hi>Rome</hi> is, and how miſerable the honour of the <hi>Ignatian</hi> Tribe is, who brag if they had not been, <hi>Rome</hi> had not been; the Angel had long ſince ſaid, <hi>It is fallen, it is fallen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>Uſe 1.</head>
               <p>Now the Uſe that every true Proteſtant is to make of this, is to render unto God his unfeigned thanks for our moſt Religious King, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> who vow and aſſert, and proteſt to ſtick to the true Chriſtian Faith once delivered to the Saints, which Faith hath been receiv'd in this Iſland of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> 1640. and upwards; <hi>i. e.</hi> ever ſince the latter years of <hi>Tiberius</hi> his Reign, who died in the 27th year of Chriſt, as <hi>Baronius</hi> reckons it. <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimathea,</hi> and <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> were the firſt Planters here; and ſome ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> preached here alſo: King <hi>Lucius</hi> in the year of Chriſt, 169. was baptized,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47158:19"/> and ſetled three Primates and Metropolitans: one in <hi>London,</hi> another in <hi>York,</hi> and the third in <hi>Caerlion</hi> in <hi>Monmouthſhire,</hi> and ever ſince we have had ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively Archbiſhops, and Biſhops in our Church of <hi>England;</hi> whereupon this Church became to be call'd of ſome <hi>Anglicana, filia Primogenita, Eccleſie Catholica.</hi> The Reform'd Chriſtian Profeſſors of Chriſts Faith were call'd <hi>Proteſtants</hi> firſt in <hi>Germany,</hi> when the Doctrine of Chriſt, by the induſtry of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon, Luther,</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> prevail'd ſo with the Princes, and Dukes there, that they have unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agreed and proteſted to ſtick to the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſuperſtitious Popery, to their Lives and Fortunes: And this Proteſtant Religion, much upon the ſame time, or ſhortly after, was profeſs'd and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>England</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, revived by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> continued by King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, all of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, and now maintained and defended by our moſt gracious Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, whom we heartily are bound to pray for, may he go on and proſper, and may his Royal Heart be ſtill in Gods good hand for it, to diſpoſe it his own good way: May his Royal Perſon, both at his going out, and at his coming in, be now and evermore, as ſafe, Body and Soul, as all the holy Angels can make him ſafe, from all pernicious Counſels, and from Counſels of falſhood and wrong.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>Uſe 2.</head>
               <p>To ſtrengthen and eſtabliſh us in this Religion, yea though it be to the hazard and loſs of Properties,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47158:20"/> and Liberties, Fortunes, and Life it ſelf; <hi>Mat. Fear not him that kills the body, but rather fear him that can deſtroy both body and ſoul in hell;</hi> put on your Spiritual Armour, fight the good fight of Faith, and finiſh the good Religious courſe that ye have begun: Conſider your Caſe and Quarrel you contend for, the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rev. 12. 17. Run, I ſay, therefore the Race with patience, looking unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of your Faith.</hi> Did <hi>Scipio</hi> ſuffer Death for vindicating the City, and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his love to Equity, and was <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd for his care of his Country? and ſhall we ſink under the weight of ſome light afflictions, which can endure but a moment, for ſo great a Caſe?</p>
               <p>3. And laſtly, becauſe our Enemies are watchful to take advantage, and rejoyce at our miſcarriages, they are like Ravens and Vultures, gathering to, and picking at our infirmities and failings,</p>
               <q>Laetetur, certe priamus, priamoque Creati.</q>
               <p>Therefore ought we to be very cautious in all our ways, and circumſpect in all our actions; <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is excellently obſerv'd of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creatures as have ſtrong and firm Bodies and Stomacks, can devour and digeſt Serpents and Frogs; let us then, quitting our ſelves like men of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Minds, ſtrong Faith, ſound Principles, and blameleſs Practiſes, ſlight and digeſt with patience the Scandals and falſe Accuſations of the Serpents
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47158:20"/> Seed, the Evil Spirits proceeding out of the Mouth of the Dragon; <hi>Let us bleſs them that curſe us, and pray for them that ſpightfully uſe us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to conclude the whole matter of what hath been ſaid, as you would eſcape the imminent danger of the dreadful Curſe of God, with pernicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions in this and the World to come, be watchful and active againſt the prevailing of Popery, which with the utmoſt rage of Perſecution is unavoidably deſtructive to Prince and Properties, Religion and Laws, Liberties and Countries, Families and Lives, yea Souls too, if we ſubſcribe to it: And as we ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the love and peace of God, the integrity of the true Chriſtian Faith, profeſs'd publickly, as once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints, and the continuance of Pious Government by juſt Laws, and have a due regard for the ſafety of his Majeſty, and for the ſtrength and preſervation of the Kingdom from Forreign Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, let us without wavering ſtick to the Proteſtant Religion, in which we have been bred and born; and God out of his abundant Grace grant we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (with courage and comfort in the Holy Ghoſt) to die in the ſame, in which (if we continue, through Faith in Chriſt) we ſhall aſſuredly find Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 15. Line 23. for provoke God ſafeſt, read provoke God faſteſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:21"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed and Sold by <hi>Iſaac Cleave,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> next to <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants-Inn</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Church of <hi>Rome</hi> unmasked, or her falſe Principles briefly detected, with ſome Reaſons of ſo many retaining or returning to Communion with her, and the great danger of everlaſting deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that ſuch do run themſelves upon: Written by a Learned Divine, by way of Letter to a Friend in the Country.</p>
            <p>The Book of Rates, now uſed in the Sin-Cuſtom-Houſe of the Church and Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> containing Bulls, Diſpenſations, and Pardons for all manner of Villanies and Wickedneſſes, with the ſeveral ſums of Money to be paid for them: To which is added the new Creed of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> containing the Articles of their Faith; by <hi>Anthony Egane,</hi> B. D. late Confeſſor of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but now of the Reformed Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi>'s Improvement Revived in a Treatiſe of (all manner of Husbandry and Trade by Land and Sea; plainly diſcovering the ſeveral ways of impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all ſorts of waſte and barren Ground, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching all Earths, with the Natural Quality of all Lands, and the ſeveral Seeds and Plants which moſt naturally thrive therein, Together with the manner of Planting all ſorts of Trees, with Directions to make Walks, Groves, Orchards, Gardens: Alſo the way for ordering of Cattel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Jo. Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47158:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
